<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2246 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2246.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3207 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3207.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC3546 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3546.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4033 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4033.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4034 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4035 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4346 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4346.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5246 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5246.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5280 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5321 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5321.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6125 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6125.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6186 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6186.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6394 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6394.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6409 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6409.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6698 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6698.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dane-srv SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dane-srv.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-dane-smtp SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-dane-smtp.xml">
]>

<!-- rfc xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext" category="exp" -->
<rfc category="exp" docName="draft-dukhovni-smtp-opportunistic-tls-01" ipr="trust200902">

<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="rfc2629.xslt" ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<front>
<title>SMTP security via opportunistic DANE TLS</title>
<author fullname="Viktor Dukhovni" initials="V." surname="Dukhovni">
<organization>Unaffiliated</organization>
<address>
<email>ietf-dane@dukhovni.org</email>
</address>
</author>
    <author initials="W.H." surname="Hardaker" fullname="Wes Hardaker">
      <organization>Parsons</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>P.O. Box 382</street>
          <city>Davis</city>
          <region>CA</region>
          <code>95617</code>
          <country>US</country>
        </postal>
        <email>ietf@hardakers.net</email>
      </address>
    </author>
<date year="2013" />
<area>sec</area>
<workgroup>DANE</workgroup>
<keyword>DANE</keyword>
<keyword>TLSA</keyword>
<keyword>SMTP</keyword>

<abstract> <t>
This memo describes a protocol for opportunistic TLS
security based on the DANE TLSA DNS record.  The design goal is an incremental
transition of the Internet email backbone (MTA to MTA SMTP traffic)
from today's unauthenticated and unencrypted connections
to TLS encrypted and authenticated delivery when the client is DANE
TLSA aware and the server domain publishes DANE TLSA records for
its MX hosts.
</t> </abstract>

</front>

<middle>
<section title="Introduction">

<section title="Background">
<t>
The Domain Name System Security Extensions (DNSSEC) add data origin
authentication and data integrity to the Domain Name System.  DNSSEC
is defined in <xref target="RFC4033"/>, <xref target="RFC4034"/> and
<xref target="RFC4035"/>.
</t>

<t>
As described in the introduction of <xref target="RFC6698"/>, TLS
authentication via the existing public Certificate Authority (CA)
Public Key Infrastructure (PKI) suffers from an
over-abundance of trusted certificate authorities capable of issuing
certificates for any domain of their choice.  DNS-Based Authentication
of Named Entities (DANE) leverages the DNSSEC infrastructure to
publish trusted keys and certificates for use with TLS via a new
TLSA record type.  DNSSEC validated DANE TLSA records
have created a new PKI designed to augment or replace the trust model of
the existing public CA PKI.
</t>

<t>
In the context of this memo, channel security is assumed to be provided
by TLS.  The Transport Layer Security (TLS) protocols provide secured
TCP communication.  Used without authentication, TLS
provides protection only against eavesdropping.  With authentication,
TLS also provides protection against man-in-the-middle (MITM) attacks.
Since the publication of the TLS 1.0 specification in <xref
target="RFC2246"/>, two updates to the protocol have been published:
TLS 1.1 <xref target="RFC4346"/> and TLS 1.2 <xref target="RFC5246"/>.
</t>

</section><!-- Background -->

<section title="SMTP Channel Security" anchor="channelsec">

<t>
The Simple Mail Transport Protocol (SMTP) (<xref target="RFC5321" />)
is multi-hop store &amp; forward, while TLS security is hop-by-hop.
The number of hops from the sender's Mail User Agent to the recipient
mailbox is rarely less than 2 and is often higher.  Some hops may be
TLS protected, some may not.  The same SMTP TCP endpoint can serve
both TLS and non-TLS clients, with TLS negotiated via the SMTP
STARTTLS command (<xref target="RFC3207"/>).  MX RRs abstract hop
destinations via DNS.  SMTP addresses are not transport addresses and
are security agnostic.  Unlike HTTP, there is no URI scheme for email
addresses to designate whether the SMTP server should be contacted
with or without security.</t>

<t>
A Mail Transport Agent (MTA) may need to forward a message to a particular email recipient
&lt;user@example.com&gt;.  To deliver the message, the MTA needs to
retrieve the MX hosts of example.com from DNS, and then deliver the
message to one of them.  Absent DNSSEC, the MX lookup is vulnerable
to man-in-the-middle and cache poisoning attacks.  As a result,
verifying MX host certificates without using DNSSEC is futile as
the attacker can simply forge DNS replies and issue bogus MX records,
directing traffic to a server of his choice.
</t>

<t>
One might try to harden STARTTLS with SMTP against DNS attacks by
requiring each MX host to posess an X.509 certificate for the
recipient domain that is obtained from the message envelope and is
not subject to DNS reply forgery.  Unfortunately, this is impractical,
as email for many domains is handled by third parties, which are
not in a position to obtain certificates for all the domains they
serve.  Deployment of SNI (see <xref target="RFC6066"/> Section
3.1) is no panacea, since the key management is operationally
challenging at large scale unless the email service provider is
also the domain's registrar and its certificate issuer; this is
rarely the case for email.
</t>

<!-- Though one counter-example suffices to demolish a conjecture,
sometimes two are better.  There are multiple insurmountable obstacles
to naive use of PKI with SMTP at Internet scale. Thus we present both
the argument above and the one below. -->

<t>
A man-in-the-middle can also suppress the MX host's STARTTLS EHLO
response.  Unless the sending MTA is statically configured to use
TLS for mail sent to example.com, the message will be sent
unauthenticated and in the clear.
Sender-side configuration of peer-domains for which TLS
must be used can protect an organization and a few of its business
partners, but is not a viable approach to securing the Internet
email backbone.  Internet email requires contacting many new domains for
which security configurations can not be established in advance.
</t>

<t>
With the existing public Certificate Authority (CA) Public Key
Infrastructure (PKI), neither the recipient domain,
nor the MX hostname are suitable SMTP server authentication identities.
Large scale deployment of authenticated TLS based on this PKI is
not possible in the context of MTA to MTA SMTP.  SMTP secure channels
authenticated via the public CA PKI are rarely used and only between domains
that make bilateral arrangements with their business partners.  At
this time, MTA to MTA traffic between Internet connected organizations
typically does not use TLS at all, or uses TLS opportunistically
without authentication, for protection only against passive
eavesdropping.
</t>

<t>
Note, the above does not apply to mail submission <xref target="RFC6409"/>,
where a mail user agent is pre-configured to send all email to a
fixed Mail Submission Agent (MSA).
Submission servers usually offer TLS and the Mail User Agent (MUA) can
be statically configured to require TLS with its chosen MSA.  The
situation changes when submission servers are configured dynamically
via SRV records (see <xref target="RFC6186"/> Section 6, although this is
not yet widely deployed).  Applications to submission
via SRV records will be discussed later in this memo.
</t>

<t>
With little opportunity to use the existing public CA PKI, MX hosts
that support STARTTLS often use self-signed or private-CA issued
X.509 certificates.  They are rarely configured with a
comprehensive list of trusted CAs and do not check CRLs or implement
OCSP.  In essence, they don't and can't use the existing public CA
PKI.  This is not simply a result of complacency on the part SMTP
server administrators and MTA developers.  Nor is it just a result
of the relative maturity of the SMTP infrastructure when TLS was
introduced. Rather, the abstraction of the SMTP transport endpoint via DNS
MX records, often across organization boundaries, limits the use
of public CA PKI with SMTP to a small set of sender-configured peer
domains.
</t>

<t>
This does not mean, however, that the Internet email backbone cannot benefit
from TLS.  The fact that transport security is not explicitly
specified in either the recipient address or the MX record means
that new protocols can furnish out-of-band information to SMTP,
making it possible to simultaneously discover both which peer domains support
secure delivery via TLS and how to verify the
authenticity of the associated MX hosts.  The first such mechanism
that can work an Internet scale is DANE TLSA, but use of DANE TLSA
with MTA to MTA SMTP must be cognizant of the lack of any realistic
role for the existing public CA PKI.
</t>

</section><!-- SMTP Channel Security -->

<section title="Terminology">

<t>
The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
"SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in
this document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
</t>

</section><!-- Terminology -->

</section><!-- Introduction -->

<section title="Hardening Opportunistic TLS">

<t>
This section describes opportunistic SMTP over TLS security, where traffic
from DANE TLSA aware SMTP clients to domains that implement DANE
TLSA records in accordance with this memo is secure.  Traffic
to other domains continues to be sent in the same manner as before
(either manually configured for security or unencrypted and unauthenticated).
It is hoped that, over time, more domains will implement DNSSEC and
publish DANE TLSA records for their MX hosts.  This will enable an
incremental transition of the email backbone to authenticated TLS
delivery.
</t>

<t>
Since email addresses and MX hostnames (or submission SRV records)
neither signal nor deny support for TLS by the receiving domain,
it is possible to use DANE TLSA records to securely signal TLS
support and simultaneously to provide the means by which SMTP clients
can successfully authenticate legitimate SMTP servers.
</t>

<section title="TLS discovery">

<t>
As noted previously (<xref target="channelsec" />),
opportunistic TLS with SMTP servers that
advertise TLS support via STARTTLS is subject to a man in the middle
downgrade attack.  Some SMTP servers erroneously advertise STARTTLS
in default configurations that are not in fact TLS capable, and
clients need to be prepared to retry plaintext delivery after
STARTTLS fails.  Downgrade resistant mechanisms for
a server to advertise TLS support via DNSSEC validated DANE TLSA
records are specified below.  DNSSEC validated TLSA records are unlikely to be published
by default for servers that do not in fact support TLS, and thus
clients can safely interpret their presence as a commitment by the
server operator to implement STARTTLS.
</t>

<t>
SMTP is a store &amp; forward protocol.  An MTA that is not the
final destination for a message recipient forwards the message one
hop closer to the recipient's mailbox.  To do so, it must determine
the appropriate next-hop destination.  
</t>

<t>
Typically, the next-hop destination defaults to the domain part of
the recipient address, which is then subject to MX resolution.  The
next-hop destination may also be configured by the MTA administrator to
be a next-hop destination host (explicitly exempt from MX resolution),
or a next-hop destination domain (subject to MX resolution), which
takes the place of the domain part of the recipient address.  In
the language of <xref target="RFC5321"/> Section 5.1, we'll refer
to this next-hop destination host or domain as "the initial name".
</t>

<section title="MX resolution">

<t>
If the initial name is a next-hop domain subject to MX resolution,
a DNSSEC validated "MX" lookup is performed, to obtain the list of
associated MX hosts.  If no MX records are found, or if if the
initial name is a next-hop host not subject to MX resolution, it
is resolved to one or more network addresses, by performing DNSSEC
validated "A" and/or "AAAA" lookups.
</t>

<t>
Following <xref target="RFC5321"/> Section 5.1, if the "A", "AAAA"
or "MX" lookup of the initial name yields a CNAME, we replace it
with the resulting name as if it were the initial name and try the
same lookup again with the new name.  MTAs typically support limited
recursion in CNAME expansion so this replacement is performed
recursively.  If initially, or at any stage of recursion, the response
is "bogus", MX resolution fails with a temporary error.  Mail delivery
SHOULD either be deferred or attempted via any alternative delivery
channel configured by the MTA administrator (which may also employ
opportunistic DANE TLS).</t>

<t>
If at any stage the response is "insecure", opportunistic DANE
TLS is not applicable, and mail delivery SHOULD proceed with pre-DANE
opportunistic TLS (subject to its various MITM attacks).
</t>

<t>
If at each and every stage the respose is "secure", and the initial
name is a next-hop host name not subject to MX resolution, the
resulting final name becomes the next-hop destination and is the
base domain for TLSA record lookup.
</t>

<t>
If at each and every stage the respose is "secure", and the initial
name is a next-hop domain subject to MX resolution, and no MX
records are found, the resulting final name is the next-hop destination
and is the base domain for TLSA record lookup.
</t>

<t>
If at each and every stage the respose is "secure", and the initial
name is a next-hop domain subject to MX resolution, and one or more
MX records are found, the MX records MUST be sorted by preference.
A better (numerically lower) MX preference for a host that does not
support TLS MUST NOT be preempted by a worse (numerically higher)
MX preference for a host that does support TLS.  In other words,
avoiding delivery loops trumps any preference for channel security.
</t>

<t>
In each delivery attempt via a candidate MX host, the MX host SHOULD
be treated as though it were the initial next-hop destination host
(which is, of course, not subject to further MX resolution) with
the associated TLSA base domain determined as above.
</t>

<t>
CNAMEs are not legal in the exchange field of MX records, thus MTAs
MAY skip over MX records in which the MX exchange is a CNAME.  There
is some additional risk, in this case, that the MTA may fail to notice
that it is one of the MX hosts for the destination and that it must
skip MX records with equal or worse (numerically higher precedence).
If an MTA does allow CNAMEs to be used in MX records it SHOULD process
them recursively as described above to determine whether opportunistic
DANE TLS is applicable and if so the associated TLSA RRset base domain.
</t>

</section><!-- MX resolution -->

<section title="tlsa record lookup">

<t>
when all the dnssec lookups, "cname", "mx", "a" or "aaaa", used to
obtain a given tlsa base domain (one for each candidate mx host if
multiple dnssec validated mx hosts were found) is "secure", and the
smtp client is configured for opportunistic dane tls, it should
locate the tlsa rrset corresponding to this base domain.   if, for
example, the base domain is "mail.example.com", the tlsa rrset is
obtained via a dnssec query of the form:
</t>

<figure>
<artwork>
_25._tcp.mail.example.com. in tlsa ?
</artwork>
</figure>

<t>
typically, the destination tcp port is 25, but this may be different
with custom routes specified by the mta administrator or when an
mua connects to a submission server on port 587.  the smtp client
must use the appropriate "_&lt;port&gt;" prefix in place of "_25"
when the port number is not equal to 25.  the query response may
be a cname (or a dname + cname combination), or the tlsa rrset.
dname processing with dnssec can be done using standard dname
resolution techniques and will not be
discussed in detail here.  the smtp client must check the security
status of the response.
</t>

<t>
if the response is "bogus", delivery via the host in question should
not proceed, otherwise the smtp client is vulnerable to man in the
middle starttls downgrade attacks.  if the response is "insecure",
opportunistic dane tls is not applicable for the host in question,
and the smtp client should proceed with legacy opportunistic tls.
<!-- xxxwjh: there is no legacy opportunistic tls; legacy tls? -->
if the response is "secure" and the record is a cname or dname,
the smtp client restarts the tlsa query at the target domain,
following cnames as appropriate.
</t>

<t>
if, after possible cname indirection, the response is "secure" and
at least one tlsa record is found (even if not usable because it is
unsupported by the implementation or administratively disabled) the
next-hop host has committed to tls support.  the smtp client
should not deliver mail via such a next-hop host unless a tls session
is negotiated via starttls.  this avoids the man in the middle starttls
downgrade attacks.
</t>

<t>
when usable tlsa records are available, a client should not deliver
mail via a server that fails to match at least one tlsa record.  this
is not a "must" because clients may incrementally deploy opportunistic
dane tls only for selected peer domains.  at times, clients may need
to disable opportunistic dane tls for peers that fail to interoperate
due to misconfiguration or software defects on either end.  for
opportunistic dane tls to be robust (resistant to failures), servers
must live up to the promises stated by the existence of the tlsa
record, but it is not always possible to compel
clients to use a security policy chosen by the server.  given a robust
security protocol, clients will hopefully, over time, willingly
choose to adopt it.
</t>

<!-- xxxwjh: the following few paragraphs (till 'end cut') can be
     removed and a reference added to -ops: "Certificate Name Check Conventions" -->
<t>
The party responsible for creating TLSA records for a given service
MUST ensure that at least one of these TLSA records will match
either the server's default certificate chain if SNI is not employed
on the server, or the server's certificate chain when the client
signals the base domain of the TLSA RRset via SNI and a name type
of "host_name" (<xref target="RFC3546"/> Section 3.1).
</t>

<t>
When, for example, the TLSA RRset is published at _25._tcp.mail.example.com
the base domain is mail.example.com.  At least one of the TLSA records
in the RRset MUST match the server certificate chain, provided the
SMTP client's TLS hanshake included the SNI extension with a domain
of mail.example.com.
</t>

<t>
Complications arise when TLSA records for a service are created by
someone other than the server operator.  In this situation the
server operator and TLSA record creator must cooperate to ensure
that TLSA records don't fall out of step with the server certificate
configuration.
</t>

<t>
When the server operator is a hosting provider, the customer's MX
records should contain the primary hostnames of the provider's SMTP
servers.  This way, any associated TLSA records will be found in
the hosting provider's DNSSEC zone, thus avoiding the complexity
of bilateral coordination of server certificate configuration and
TLSA record management.  If the customer's DNS zone is signed, the
provider hostnames in customer domain's MX records can be securely
used as the base names for locating TLSA records managed by the
hosting provider.
</t>

<t>
Redirection of SMTP service from one domain to another is usually
accomplished via MX records (or perhaps SRV records in the case of
submission).  Alternatively, the domain part of an email address
may be a CNAME (see <xref target="RFC5321"/> Section 2.3.5).
CNAMEs are a more blunt instrument for this purpose, since unlike
MX or SRV records they remap the origin domain to the target domain for
all protocols.  Also Unlike MX or SRV records CNAME records may
chain (though clients will generally impose implementation dependent
maximum nesting depths).
</t>

<t>
Though CNAMEs are illegal on the right hand side of MX and SRV
records, they are supported by some SMTP software.  They arise most
frequently with submission clients or when an administrator configures
an explicit next-hop destination host and that host happens to be
an alias.  If the MX or SRV host is a CNAME alias from a customer's
domain to a server in the provider's domain, the client SHOULD
follow the CNAME and SHOULD use the target hostname as the base
domain for TLSA records as well as the host_name in SNI.  
</t>

<t>
Treating CNAMEs in MX hosts in the same manner as CNAMEs with non-MX
destinations is consistent with <xref target="RFC5321"/> where non-MX
destinations are considered equivalent to destinations with a single
preference 0 MX record with the query domain identical to the MX host.
</t>

<t>
When CNAMEs are employed the sensible place to seek DANE TLSA records
is in the provider's domain, as the provider knows best which
certificates are deployed on the server.  Therefore, clients
implementing opportunistic DANE TLS when connecting to a server whose
DNS name is a CNAME SHOULD follow the CNAME hop-by-hop to its
ultimate target host (noting at each step whether the CNAME is
DNSSEC validated) and use the resulting target host as the base
domain for TLSA lookups.
</t>

<t>
If CNAMEs were not followed, to support DANE validation the origin
domain would have to publish TLSA records that match the server
certificate chain.  Since the origin domain may not administer
the server this imposes a difficult key management burden
on the provider and customer even with SNI.
</t>

<t>
Accordingly, TLSA records SHOULD NOT be published for a base domain
that is a CNAME.  Such TLSA records may not reliably verify,
and SHOULD NOT be used by opportunistic SMTP DANE TLS clients.
</t>

<t>
It may be tempting to publish CNAMEs in the hosted domain pointing
to the provider's TLSA RRset.  This only works when the provider's TLSA
RRs specify certificate usage 3.  Otherwise, an SMTP client that
used the alias name (from the hosted rather than the provider's domain)
as the base domain to obtain the TLSA RRset would look for the
hosted domain in the server certificate when performing name
checks, and would generally fail to authenticate the server except
in the rare cases when the server's certificate does include the
hosted domain.
</t>

<figure>
<artwork>
; TLSA RRs aliased to provider, but the base domain is the hosted
; domain.  Likely to fail name check unless provider usage is "3".
;
_25._tcp.mail.example.com. IN CNAME _25._tcp.mail.example.net.
</artwork>
</figure>

<!-- XXXWJH: end cut -->

</section><!-- TLSA record lookup -->
</section><!-- TLS discovery -->

<section title="DANE authentication">

<section title="TLSA certificate usages">

<t>
As noted in the introduction, the existing public CA PKI is not
viable for the Internet email backbone.  TLSA records for MX hosts
or submission servers that are to be found via SRV records SHOULD
NOT include certificate usage "0" or "1", as in both cases SMTP
clients cannot be expected to perform <xref target="RFC5280"/> PKIX
validation or <xref target="RFC6125"/> identity verification.
</t>

<t>
If despite this recommendation SMTP servers do publish TLSA records
with certificate usage "0" or "1", clients SHOULD make use of these
to the fullest extent possible.
</t>

<t>
With any of the certificate usages described below, server operators
should generally avoid publishing "TLSA * 0 0" records as even a
single certificate is generally too large to be reliably delivered
via DNS.  Two full certificates may need to be published in the TLSA
RRset for certificate rollover.
</t>

<t>
While "TLSA * 1 0" records that publish full public keys are generally
more compact, these too should be used with caution, for example
two 2048-bit RSA keys require more than 512 bytes of DNS data, and
thus don't fit into the default 512-byte limit for DNS UDP replies.
Servers SHOULD publish the certificate or key digest via DNS, with
the complete key or certificate communicated in band during the TLS
handshake.
</t>

<section title="Certificate usage 3">

<t>
Since opportunistic DANE TLS will be used by non-interactive MTAs,
with no user to "press OK" when authentication fails, reliability
of peer authentication is paramount.  The recommended choice of
TLSA record type for opportunistic DANE TLS is "3 1 1".  This record
specifies the SHA-256 digest of the server's public key.
</t>

<t>
Authentication via certificate usage "3" TLSA records involves no
certificate authority signature checks as no CA is explicitly
trusted.  It also involves no server name checks, and thus does not
a impose any new requirements on the names contained in the server
certificate (SNI not required when the TLSA record matches the
public key of the server's default certificate).  It uses the SHA-256
digest which all clients are obligated to support, and works across
certificate renewals with the same key.  TLSA records for SMTP
servers SHOULD typically be "3 1 1" records.
</t>

<t>
Two such records need to be published before updating the server's
public key, one matching the currently deployed key and the other
matching the new key scheduled to replace it.  Once sufficient time
has elapsed for all caches to time out the previous TLSA RRset which
contains only the old key the server may be reconfigured to use the
new private key and associated public key certificate.  The zone
signature validity time provides an upper bound on the time required).
Once the server is using a new key, the obsolete TLSA RR can be removed
from DNS, leaving only the RR that matches the new key.
</t>

</section><!-- Certificate usage 3 -->

<section title="Certificate usage 2">

<t>
Some domains may prefer to reduce the operational complexity of
publishing unique TLSA RRs for each TLS service.  If the domain
employs a common issuing certificate authority to create certificates
for multiple TLS services, it may be simpler to publish the issuing
authority's public key as a trust-anchor for the certificate chains
of all relevant services.  The TLSA RRs for each service issued by
the same TA may then be CNAMEs to a common TLSA RRset that matches
the TA.  In this case, the TLS handshake trust chain of each service
SHOULD include the TA certificate, as SMTP clients cannot generally
be expected to have domain-issued trust-anchor certificates in their
trusted certificate store.  The recommended record type in this
case is either "2 1 1" or "2 0 1", which specifies the SHA-256 digest
of the trust-anchor public key or certificate.  Two such TLSA RRs need
to be published to facilitate TA certificate rollover.
</t>

<t>
The usability of "2 1 1" or "2 0 1" TLSA RRs with SMTP is not assured.
If server operators emplying these RRs almost universally ensure that
the corresponding TA certificate is included in the SMTP server's TLS
handshake trust chain, then clients will enable support for these RRs.
If sufficiently many server administrators are negligent in deploying
these RRs, SMTP clients may be hesitant to support them since mail
delivery will not work to many destination domains if they do.  We
encourage server operators to implement these RRs if appropriate to
their organization, provided they do so with care.  Never forget
to include trust-anchor certificates in server trust chains.
We encourage SMTP client implementations to support these TLSA RRs
by default, unless future experience proves our optimism unfounded.
</t>

<t>
Clients employing opportunistic DANE TLS MAY choose to treat any
TLSA records with certificate usage "0" as unusable.  They may then
choose to connect via unauthenticated mandatory TLS if no alternative
authentication mechanisms are available.
</t>

</section><!-- Certificate usage 2 -->

<section title="Certificate usage 1">

<t>
SMTP servers SHOULD NOT publish TLSA RRs with certificate usage "1".
SMTP clients that implement this specification SHOULD ignore the
PKIX validation requirement when they encounter certificate usage
"1", and SHOULD authenticate the server per the content of the TLSA
record alone.  That is, as with certificate usage "3", clients
SHOULD NOT apply name checks, expiration checks, or process the
server certificate content beyond possibly extracting its public
key for matching against corresponding TLSA RRs.
</t>

</section><!-- Certificate usage 1 -->

<section title="Certificate usage 0">

<t>
SMTP servers SHOULD NOT publish TLSA RRs with certificate usage "0".
Since PKIX validation is not possible with opportunistic DANE TLS,
SMTP clients SHOULD treat certificate usage "0" RRs as though they
were certificate usage "2" RRs, but with certificate usage "0" the
usability of the TLSA record depends more strongly on its matching
type.  Name checks, key usage checks, ... apply identically to the
leaf certificate with TLSA usages "0" and "2".
</t>

<t>
If the matching type is "0" (the server also avoid this matching
type and should publish usage "3" or "2" public key or certificate
digests) the TLSA record contains the full certificate or full
public key of the trusted certificate authority.  In this case the
client has all the information it needs to match the server trust-chain
to the TLSA record.  The client SHOULD in this case ignore the PKIX
validation requirement, and verify the server's trust chain via its DANE
TLSA records only (name checks still apply as with usage "2").
</t>

<t>
If the matching type is not "0", the TLSA record contains only a
digest of the trust certificate authority certificate or public
key.  The server operator publishing usage 0 TLSA records may expect
that clients already have the issuing authority certificate on hand,
and may omit it from the server's certificate chain.  As a result
the client may not be able to match the server trust chain against
the TLSA record.
</t>

<t>
SMTP clients that implement this specification SHOULD generally
treat TLSA records with certificate usage "0" and a digest matching
type as unusable, but MAY be explicitly configured to support them
when it is believed that the client posesses a sufficiently complete
set of trusted public CA certificates.  This is most plausible with
an MUA which only needs enough CA certificates to authenticate its
preferred submission service.
</t>

</section><!-- Certificate usage 0 -->

</section><!-- TLSA certificate usages -->

<section title="Certificate matching">
<t>
When at least one usable "secure" TLSA record is found, the SMTP
client SHOULD use TLSA records to authenticate the next-hop host,
mail SHOULD not be delivered via this next-hop host if authentication
fails, otherwise the SMTP client is vulnerable to TLS man in the
middle attacks.
</t>

<t>
With TLSA certificate usages "2" or "0" the TLSA base domain SHOULD
be the domain the client looks for in the server certificate to
check that it has reached the correct server, if the TLSA base domain
was obtained indirectly via an MX lookup, the CNAME resolved name used
in the MX lookup SHOULD also be accepted.  Barring CNAME expansion,
this additional domain is typically the envelope recipient domain,
but may be different when the client is an MUA sending all mail to
a submission server, or an MTA configured with explicit next-hop
destination overrides for the message recipient.
</t>

<t>
Accepting certificates witih the next-hop domain in addition to the
next-hop MX host allows a domain with multiple MX hosts to field a
single certificate bearing the email domain name across all the MX
hosts, this is also compatible with pre-DANE SMTP clients that are
configured to look for the email domain name in server certificates.
</t>

<t>
The client MUST NOT perform certificate usage name checks with
certificate usage "3" (or equivalently "1"), since with these the
server is authenticated directly by matching the TLSA RRset to its
certificate or public key without resort to any issuing authority.
The certificate content is ignored except in so far as it is used
to match the certificate with the TLSA RRset.
</t>

<t>
To ensure that the server sends the right certificate chain, the
SMTP client MUST send the TLS SNI extension containing the TLSA
base domain.  Since DANE-aware clients are obligated to send SNI
information, which requires at least TLS 1.0, SMTP servers for which
DANE TLSA records are published MUST support TLS 1.0 or later with
any client authorized to use the service.
</t>

<t>
Each SMTP server MUST present a certificate trust chain (see <xref
target="RFC2246"/> Section 7.4.2) that matches at least
one of the TLSA records.  The server MAY rely on SNI to determine
which certificate chain to present to the client.  Clients that
don't send SNI information may not see the expected certificate
chain.
</t>

<t>
If the server's TLSA RRset includes records with a matching type
other than "0" (digest records), the SHA-256 digest of any
object SHOULD be provided along with any other digest published,
since clients may support only SHA-256.  Unless SHA-256 proves
vulnerable to a "second preimage" attack, it should be the only
digest algorithm used in TLSA records.
</t>

<t>
If the server's TLSA records match the server's default certificate
chain, the server need not support SNI.  The server need not include
the extension in its TLS HELLO, simply returning a matching certificate
chain is sufficient.  Servers MUST NOT enforce the use of SNI by
clients, if the client sends no SNI extension, or sends an SNI
extension for an unsupported domain the server MUST simply use its
default certificate chain.  The client may be using unauthenticated
opportunistic TLS and may not expect any particular certificate
from the server.  </t>

<t>
The client may even offer to use anonymous TLS ciphersuites
and servers SHOULD support these, no security is gained by forcing
the use of a certificate the client will ignore.  Indeed support
for anonymous ciphersuites in the server makes audit trails more
useful if the chosen ciphersuite is logged, as this will in many
cases record which clients did not care to authenticate the server.
(The Postfix SMTP server supports anonymous TLS ciphersuites by
default, and the Postfix SMTP client offers these at its highest
preference when server authentication is not applicable).
</t>

<t>
With opportunistic DANE TLS, both the TLS support implied by the
presence of DANE TLSA records and the verification parameters
necessary to authenticate the TLS peer are obtained together,
therefore authentication via this protocol is expected to be less
prone to connection failure caused by incompatible configuration
of the client and server.
</t>

</section><!-- Certificate matching -->
</section><!-- DANE authentication -->
</section><!-- Hardening Opportunistic TLS -->

<section title="Opportunistic TLS for Submission">

<t>
Prior to <xref target="RFC6409"/>, the SMTP submission protocol was
poster child for PKIX TLS.  The MUA typically connects to one or more 
submission servers explicitly configured by the
user.  There is no indirection via insecure MX records, and unlike
web browsers, there is no need to authenticate a large set of TLS servers.
Once TLS is enabled for the desired submission server or servers,
provided the server certificate is correctly maintained, the MUA
is able to reliably use TLS to authenticate the submission server.
</t>

<t>
<xref target="RFC6409"/> aims to simplify the configuration of the MUA
submission service by dynamically deriving the submission service from
the user's email address.  This is done via SRV records, but at the cost
of introducing the same TLS security problems faced by MTA to MTA SMTP.
Prompting the user when the SRV record domain is different from the email
domain is not a robust solution.
</t>

<t>
The protocol defined in this memo can also be used to opportunistically secure
the submission service association.  If the email domain is DNSSEC signed,
the SRV records are "secure" and the SRV host publishes secure TLSA records
for submission, then the MUA can safely auto-configure to authenticate the
submission server via DANE.  When DANE TLSA records are not available, the
client SHOULD fall back to legacy behavior.
</t>

</section><!-- Opportunistic TLS for Submission -->

<section title="Mandatory TLS Security">

<t>
An MTA implementing this protocol for sending email to the internet
at large may need a greater security assurance when sending email
to selected destinations to which the sending organization sends
sensitive email and may have regulatory obligations to protect its
content.  This protocol is not in conflict with this requirement,
in fact it can often simplify authenticated delivery to such
destinations.
</t>

<t>
Specifically, with domains that publish DANE TLSA records for their MX hosts
a sending MTA can be configured to use the receiving domains's DANE TLSA
records to authenticate the corresponding MX hosts, thereby obviating a
complex manual provisioning process.  In anticipation of or in response to
failure to obtain the expected TLSA records the sending system's
administrator may choose from a menu of fallback options if supported by the
sending MTA:
</t>

<t>
<list style="symbols">

<t>
Defer mail if no usable TLSA records are found.  This is useful when the
destination is known to publish TLSA records, and lack of TLSA records is
most likely a transient misconfiguration.
</t>

<t>
Authenticate the peer via a manually configured certificate digest.  The
digest may be a saved copy from a previous successful TLSA lookup, or may be
obtained after a problem is detected and confirmed to be valid by some
out-of-band mechanism.
</t>

<t>
Authenticate the peer via the existing public CA PKI, if the peer server has
usable CA issued certificates.  In many cases the sending MTA will need
custom certificate name matching rules to match the destination's gateways.
</t>

<t>
Send via unauthenticated mandatory TLS.  If the requirement is merely to
always encrypt, and the possibility of MITM attacks is less of a concern
than timely email delivery.
</t>

</list>
</t>

<t>
It should be noted that barring administrator intervention email
SHOULD be deferred when DNSSEC lookups fail, (as distinct from
"secure" non-existence of TLSA records, or secure evidence that the
domain is no longer signed).  In addition to configuring fallback
strategies when TLSA records are unexpectedly absent administrators
may in some cases need to disable DNSSEC lookups for a destination
to work around a DNSSEC outage.
</t>

</section><!-- Mandatory TLS Security -->

<section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">

<t>
Thanks to Tony Finch who finally prodded me into participating in
DANE working group discussions. Thanks to Paul Hoffman who motivated
me to produce this memo and provided feedback on early drafts.
Thanks also to Wietse Venema who created Postfix, and patiently
guided the Postfix DANE implementation to production quality.
</t>

</section><!-- Acknowledgements -->

<section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">

<t>
This protocol leverages DANE TLSA records to implement MITM resistant
opportunistic channel security for SMTP.  For destination domains
that sign their MX records and publish signed TLSA records for their
MX hosts this protocol allows sending MTAs (and perhaps dynamically
configured MUAs) to securely discover both the availability of TLS
and how to authenticate the destination.
</t>

<t>
This protocol does not aim to secure all SMTP traffic, that will
not be practical until DNSSEC and DANE adoption are universal
(universal SMTP TLS security via the existing public CA PKI is even
less realistic).  The fact that it can be deployed incrementally
is a feature, not a bug.  This protocol coexists and interoperates
with the existing insecure Internet email backbone, if the protocol
proves successful, a growing portion of email traffic will be
protected over time.
</t>

<t>
The protocol does not preclude existing non-opportunistic SMTP TLS security
arrangements, these can continue as before, or may be used as fallback
strategies when this protocol fails to locate the desired security
parameters.
</t>

</section><!-- Security Considerations -->

</middle>

<back>
<references title="Normative References">
&RFC2119;
&RFC2246;
&RFC3207;
&RFC3546;
&RFC4033;
&RFC4034;
&RFC4035;
&RFC4346;
&RFC5246;
&RFC5280;
&RFC5321;
&RFC6125;
&RFC6186;
&RFC6409;
&RFC6698;
</references>
<!--
<references title="Informative References">
&RFC6394;
&I-D.ietf-dane-srv;
&I-D.ietf-dane-smtp;
</references>
-->
</back>
</rfc>
